<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Women In Italian Cinema</title><link>https://example.com/</link><atom:link href="https://example.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Women In Italian Cinema</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://example.com/media/logo_hudf53cb4968ce8f451f5b6e1d5b7f4ffc_232652_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url><title>Women In Italian Cinema</title><link>https://example.com/</link></image><item><title>About</title><link>https://example.com/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/about/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Accessibility</title><link>https://example.com/accessibility/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/accessibility/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Advisory</title><link>https://example.com/advisory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/advisory/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://example.com/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/contact/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Cookies</title><link>https://example.com/cookies/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/cookies/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Digital</title><link>https://example.com/digital/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/digital/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Documentaries</title><link>https://example.com/documentaries/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/documentaries/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Exhibitions</title><link>https://example.com/exhibitions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/exhibitions/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Introduction</title><link>https://example.com/introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/introduction/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Partners</title><link>https://example.com/partners/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/partners/</guid><description/></item><item><title>People</title><link>https://example.com/people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/people/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Publications</title><link>https://example.com/publications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/publications/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Questions</title><link>https://example.com/questions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/questions/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Research</title><link>https://example.com/methods/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/methods/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Upcoming Events</title><link>https://example.com/upcoming-eventsold/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/upcoming-eventsold/</guid><description/></item><item><title>An example preprint / working paper</title><link>https://example.com/publication/preprint/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/publication/preprint/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Add the publication&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong>full text&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>supplementary notes&lt;/strong> here. You can use rich formatting such as including &lt;a href="https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">code, math, and images&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>An example journal article</title><link>https://example.com/publication/journal-article/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/publication/journal-article/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Add the publication&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong>full text&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>supplementary notes&lt;/strong> here. You can use rich formatting such as including &lt;a href="https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">code, math, and images&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>An example conference paper</title><link>https://example.com/publication/conference-paper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/publication/conference-paper/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Add the publication&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong>full text&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>supplementary notes&lt;/strong> here. You can use rich formatting such as including &lt;a href="https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">code, math, and images&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title/><link>https://example.com/admin/config.yml</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/admin/config.yml</guid><description/></item><item><title>Archival experiences: Cecilia Mangini and Mara Blasetti</title><link>https://example.com/post/archival-experiences/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/post/archival-experiences/</guid><description>&lt;p>Entering a personal archive means gaining access to someone’s life, meeting someone unknown before and, in a certain sense, invading a personal space. Depending on the type of archive, you will find more or less personal objects and documents, but all of them tell a story, an individual’s story. Sometimes this story is strongly related to his or her work, but in some instances it is more personal. For this reason, it is with a sort of reverential respect, almost on tiptoe, that I inspect and rummage into someone’s papers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My last experience with personal archives concerns two women that played a significant role in the history of Italian cinema: Cecilia Mangini and Mara Blasetti, whose collections are held at the Cineteca of Bologna. As part of my work within the Women in Italian Film Production project, my task was to examine their archives and select materials for digitalization. The materials were selected with the aim of showing these women’s lives and work behind the scenes, while also revealing how they viewed and remembered their work. What did they do? How did they work? How did they consider their work? Did they value what they did? Did they consider it worthy of being taken as a model by future generations? With all these questions in mind, I started searching and researching.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What I found were two worlds, two lives, two women who did their job with passion and dedication. Mangini’s archive (that is actually the Mangini-Del Fra collection, and includes the work she did with her husband) is bigger than Blasetti’s, and it shows more aspects of the private sphere, such as letters exchanged with her husband in which both archival research and moments of their personal lives are discussed. The archive collects many documents related to her husband’s work, but fortunately also many papers and materials related to hers - which gives us a chance to get to know her and her work behind the camera.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Blasetti’s archive, on the contrary, collects a lot of working materials, brochures, working plans, and so on. At first glance, this seems a much more professional archive. However, it hides something very personal, which reveals Blasetti’s personality: it contains many of her planners, in which she noted down a great deal of information about her life. She was an obsessive writer, and used to take notes of every event, from a simple breakfast with a friend to a working lunch with a colleague.
Mangini’s and Blasetti’s archives are so different and so alike at the same time. They both were created and organised by their owners, and reveal some aspects of these female professionals&amp;rsquo; personalities. They are not only a testimony of their work, but also a representation of themselves. Thanks to these archives, I had the opportunity to meet a director and photographer - Mangini - and a production supervisor - Blasetti - and, above all, two women who dedicated a significant part of themselves to Italian cinema.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://womeninitaliancinema.org/author/clara-giannini">Clara Giannini&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Interviewing Women in Italian Cinema</title><link>https://example.com/post/interviews/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/post/interviews/</guid><description>&lt;p>I’ve been a journalist for twenty-five years. In my career I’ve interviewed many film professionals, mostly directors, but the Women in Italian Film Production project was such a different experience for me.For the project, with my colleagues Daniela Treveri Gennari and Silvia Dibeltulo, I conducted thirty-eight interviews with female film professionals working in the Italian film industry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All the interviewees were asked a series of standardized questions, which, although it may seem like a boring practice, is an effective method to detect trends, similarities and differences in their experiences. Asking the right questions in a confidential environment is the key to understanding their personality and life choices.
The group of people we spoke to is composed of producers, heads of production, distributors, VFX artists, costume designers, casting directors, continuity supervisors, assistant directors: all below- the-line female workers . Despite their different roles, the ways in which they describe their work and experience are often similar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was struck by how often the following topics recur in their testimonies:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>&lt;li>Fate: most of them started to work in the film industry by chance, without having planned it. Some of them sent a last-minute application for the Italian National School of Cinema (CSC), while not being entirely confident that they would be successful in their attempt.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Passion: they smile a lot while talking about their work. It looks like it’s one of the most important things in their life, if not the most important one.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Professionalism: all these women are very independent, since they have built their careers on their own. They want to be recognized for the quality of their work, just like their male colleagues are.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fun: working on set is tiring and stressful, because of long shifts and psychological pressure, but this doesn’t matter, as the upside is that they have a lot of fun. According to their statements, working in the film industry is a source of unique experiences, interesting encounters, and unforgettable moments of collective fun.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Family: they mean the family that gets created while shooting a film, when 100 to 200 people strive together towards a creative goal. This kind of partnership can be very powerful and sometimes almost more important than your own family. For some of these women the family built on set is the family they choose.&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The photo chosen for this blog post was taken during one of the interviews. It is a motto adopted by one of our interviewees that means &amp;ldquo;Ignore your responsibilities. Pretend to be dead.&amp;rdquo; It is a way out that women should practice more, as animals do, instead of always being ready and present.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://womeninitaliancinema.org/author/barbara-corsi/">Barbara Corsi&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Journal of Italian Cinema &amp; Media Studies International Conference: Re-examining the past and envisioning the future of Italian cinema and media</title><link>https://example.com/event/rome/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/event/rome/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Journal of Italian Cinema &amp; Media Studies International Conference: Re-examining the past and envisioning the future of Italian cinema and media</title><link>https://example.com/past-events/test/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/past-events/test/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Audience Project seminar talk</title><link>https://example.com/upcoming-events/cinema-ritrovato/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/upcoming-events/cinema-ritrovato/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Women In Film Production: Methods, Comparisons, Resources</title><link>https://example.com/event/warwick/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/event/warwick/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Women In Film Test</title><link>https://example.com/upcoming-events/creative-industries-festival/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://example.com/upcoming-events/creative-industries-festival/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>